The goal here is simple, explain what a
derivative is.
The thing is though, there's some
subtlety to this topic and a lot of
potential for paradoxes if you're not
careful. So kind of a secondary goal is
that you have an appreciation for what
those paradoxes are and how to avoid
them.
You see, it's common for people to say
that the derivative measures an
instantaneous rate of change. But when
you think about it, that phrase is
actually an oxymoron. Change is
something that happens between separate
points in time and when you blind
yourself to all but just a single
instant, there's not really any room for
change.
You'll see what I mean more as we get
into it, but when you appreciate that a
phrase like instantaneous rate of change
is actually nonsense, I think it makes
you appreciate just how clever the
fathers of calculus were in capturing
the idea that that phrase is meant to
evoke, but with a perfectly sensible
piece of math, the derivative.
As our central example, I want you to
imagine a car that starts at some point
A, speeds up, and then slows down to a
stop at some point B 100 m away. And
let's say it all happens over the course
of 10 seconds.
That's the setup to have in mind as we
lay out what the derivative is.
We could graph this motion, letting the
vertical axis represent the distance
traveled and the horizontal axis
represent time.
So at each time T, represented with a
point somewhere on this horizontal axis,
the height of the graph tells us how far
the car has traveled in total after that
amount of time.
It's pretty common to name a distance
function like this S of T.
I would use the letter D for distance,
but that guy already has another
full-time job in calculus.
Initially, this curve is quite shallow
since the car is slow to start. During
that first second, the distance that it
travels doesn't really change that much.
Then for the next few seconds, as the
car speeds up, the distance traveled in
a given second gets larger, which
corresponds to a steeper slope in this
graph.
And then towards the end, when it slows
down, that curve shallows out again.
And if we were to plot the car's
velocity in meters per second as a
function of time, it might look like
this bump.
At early times, the velocity is very
small. Up to the middle of the journey,
the car builds up to some maximum
velocity, covering a relatively large
distance each second.
Then it slows back down towards the
speed of zero.
And these two curves here are definitely
related to each other, right? If you
change the specific distance versus time
function, you're going to have some
different velocity versus time function.
And what we want to understand is the
specifics of that relationship. Exactly
how does velocity depend on a distance
versus time function?
And to do that, it's worth taking a
moment to think critically about what
exactly velocity means here.
Intuitively, we all might know what
velocity at a given moment means. It's
just whatever the car's speedometer
shows in that moment.
And intuitively, it might make sense
that the car's velocity should be higher
at times when this distance function is
steeper, when the car traverses more
distance per unit time.
But the funny thing is, velocity at a
single moment makes no sense. If I show
you a picture of a car, just a snapshot
in an instant, and I ask you how fast
it's going, you'd have no way of telling
me.
What you'd need are two separate points
in time to compare.
That way you can compute whatever the
change in distance across those times
is, divided by the change in time.
Right? I mean, that's what velocity is.
It's the distance traveled per unit
time.
So, how is it that we're looking at a
function for velocity that only takes in
a single value of T, a single snapshot
in time?
It's weird, isn't it? We want to
associate individual points in time with
a velocity, but actually computing
velocity requires comparing two separate
points in times.
If that feels strange and paradoxical,
good. You're grappling with the same
conflicts that the fathers of calculus
did. And if you want a deep
understanding for rates of change, not
just for a moving car, but for all sorts
of things in science, you're going to
need to resolve this apparent paradox.
First, I think it's best to talk about
the real world, and then we'll go into a
purely mathematical one.
Let's think about what the car's
speedometer is probably doing.
At some point, say 3 seconds into the
journey, the speedometer might measure
how far the car goes in a very small
amount of time. Maybe the distance
traveled between 3 seconds and 3.01
seconds.
Then, it could compute the speed in
meters per second as that tiny distance
traversed in meters divided by that tiny
time, 0.01 seconds.
That is, a physical car just sidesteps
the paradox and doesn't actually compute
speed at a single point in time. It
computes speed during a very small
amount of time.
So, let's call that difference in time
dt, which you might think of in this
case as 0.01 seconds. And let's call
that resulting difference in distance
ds.
So, the velocity at some point in time
is ds divided by dt, the tiny change in
distance over the tiny change in time.
Graphically, you can imagine zooming in
on some point of this distance versus
time graph above T equals 3.
That dt is a small step to the right,
since time is on the horizontal axis.
And that ds is the resulting change in
the height of the graph, since the
vertical axis represents the distance
traveled.
So, ds / dt
is something you can think of as the
rise over run slope between two very
close points on this graph.
Of course, there's nothing special about
the value t = 3. We could apply this to
any other point in time, so we consider
this expression ds/dt to be a function
of t. Something where I can give you a
time t and you can give me back the
value of this ratio at that time, the
velocity as a function of time.
So, for example, when I had the computer
draw this bump curve here, the one
representing the velocity function,
here's what I had the computer actually
do.
First, I chose a small value for dt. I
think in this case it was 0.01.
Then, I had the computer look at a whole
bunch of times t between 0 and 10 and
compute the distance function s at t +
dt and then subtract off the value of
that function at t.
In other words, that's the difference in
the distance traveled between the given
time t and the time 0.01 seconds after
that.
Then, you can just divide that
difference by the change in time, dt,
and that gives you velocity in m/s
around each point in time.
So, with a formula like this, you could
give the computer any curve representing
any distance function s(t) and it could
figure out the curve representing
velocity.
So, now would be a good time to pause,
reflect, make sure that this idea of
relating distance to velocity by looking
at tiny changes makes sense. Because
what we're going to do is tackle the
paradox of the derivative head on.
This idea of ds/dt, a tiny change in the
value of the function s divided by the
tiny change in the input that caused it,
that's almost what a derivative is.
And even though a car's speedometer will
actually look at a concrete change in
time like 0.01 seconds. And even though
the drawing program here is looking at
an actual concrete change in time,
in pure math, the derivative is not this
ratio ds/dt for a specific choice of dt.
Instead, it's whatever that ratio
approaches as your choice for dt
approaches zero.
Luckily, there is a really nice visual
understanding for what it means to ask
what this ratio approaches.
Remember, for any specific choice of dt,
this ratio ds/dt is the slope of a line
passing through two separate points on
the graph, right?
Well, as dt approaches zero, and as
those two points approach each other,
the slope of the line approaches the
slope of a line that's tangent to the
graph at whatever point t we're looking
at.
So, the true, honest-to-goodness, pure
math derivative is not the rise-over-run
slope between two nearby points on the
graph. It's equal to the slope of a line
tangent to the graph at a single point.
Now, notice what I'm not saying. I'm not
saying that the derivative is whatever
happens when dt is infinitely small,
whatever that would mean.
Nor am I saying that you plug in zero
for dt.
This dt is always a finitely small,
non-zero value. It's just that it
approaches zero as all.
I think that's really clever. Even
though change in an instant makes no
sense, this idea of letting dt approach
zero is a really sneaky back door way to
talk reasonably about the rate of change
at a single point in time.
Isn't that neat? It's kind of flirting
with the paradox of change in an instant
without ever needing to actually touch
it. And it comes with such a nice visual
intuition, too, as the slope of a
tangent line to a single point on the
graph.
And because change in an instant still
makes no sense, I think it's healthiest
for you to think of the slope not as
some instantaneous rate of change, but
instead as the best constant
approximation for a rate of change
around a point.
By the way, it's worth saying a couple
words on notation here. Throughout this
video, I've been using dt to refer to a
tiny change in t with some actual size
and ds to refer to the resulting change
in s, which again has an actual size.
And this is because that's how I want
you to think about them.
But the convention in calculus is that
whenever you're using the letter d like
this, you're kind of announcing your
intention that eventually you're going
to see what happens as dt approaches
zero.
For example, the honest-to-goodness pure
math derivative is written as ds divided
by dt, even though it's technically not
a fraction per se, but whatever that
fraction approaches for smaller and
smaller nudges in t.
I think a specific example should help
here.
You might think that asking about what
this ratio approaches for smaller and
smaller values would make it much more
difficult to compute. But weirdly, it
kind of makes things easier.
Let's say that you have a given distance
versus time function that happens to be
exactly t cubed. So, after 1 second, the
car has traveled 1 cubed equals 1 m.
After 2 seconds, it's traveled 2 cubed
or 8 m and so on.
Now, what I'm about to do might seem
somewhat complicated, but once the dust
settles, it really is simpler. And more
importantly, it's the kind of thing that
you only ever have to do once in
calculus.
Let's say you wanted to compute the
velocity ds divided by dt at some
specific time like t equals 2.
And for right now, let's think of dt as
having an actual size, some concrete
nudge. We'll let it go to zero in just a
bit.
The tiny change in distance between 2
seconds and 2 plus dt seconds, well,
that's s of 2 plus dt minus s of 2.
And we divide that by dt.
Since our function is t cubed, that
numerator looks like 2 + dt cubed - 2
cubed.
And this This is something we can work
out algebraically. Again, bear with me.
There's a reason that I'm showing you
the details here.
When you expand that top, what you get
is 2 cubed + 3 * 2 squared dt
+ 3 * 2 * dt squared
+ dt cubed and all of that is - 2 cubed.
Now, there's a lot of terms, and I want
you to remember that it looks like a
mess, but it does simplify.
Those 2 cubed terms, they cancel out.
And then everything remaining here has a
dt in it. And since there's a dt on the
bottom there, many of those cancel out
as well.
What this means is that the ratio ds /
dt has boiled down into 3 * 2 squared
plus Well, two different terms that each
have a dt in them.
So, if we ask what happens as dt
approaches zero, representing the idea
of looking at a smaller and smaller
change in time, we can just completely
ignore those other terms.
By eliminating the need to think about a
specific dt, we've actually eliminated a
lot of the complication in the full
expression.
So, what we're left with is this nice
clean 3 * 2 squared.
You can think of that as meaning that
the slope of a line tangent to the point
at t = 2 of this graph is exactly 3 * 2
squared, or 12.
And of course, there's nothing special
about the time t = 2. We could more
generally say that the derivative of t
cubed as a function of t is 3 * t
squared.
Now, take a step back because that's
beautiful. The derivative is this crazy
complicated idea. We've got tiny changes
in distance over tiny changes in time,
but instead of looking at any specific
one of those, we're talking about what
that thing approaches. I mean, that's a
lot to think about. And yet, what we've
come out with is such a simple
expression, 3 * t squared.
And in practice, you wouldn't go through
all this algebra each time. Knowing that
the derivative of t cubed is 3t squared
is one of those things that all calculus
students learn how to do immediately
without having to re-derive it each
time. And in the next video, I'm going
to show you a nice way to think about
this and a couple other derivative
formulas in really nice geometric ways.
But the point I want to make by showing
you all of the algebraic guts here is
that when you consider the tiny change
in distance caused by a tiny change in
time for some specific value of dt,
you'd have kind of a mess. But when you
consider what that ratio approaches as
dt approaches zero, it lets you ignore
much of that mess, and it really does
simplify the problem.
That right there is kind of the heart of
why calculus becomes useful.
Another reason to show you a concrete
derivative like this is that it sets the
stage for an example of the kind of
paradoxes that come about if you believe
too much in the illusion of
instantaneous rate of change.
So, think about the actual car traveling
according to this t cubed distance
function, and consider its motion at the
moment t equals zero, right at the
start.
Now, ask yourself whether or not the car
is moving at that time.
On the one hand, we can compute its
speed at that point using the
derivative, 3t squared, which for time t
equals zero works out to be zero.
Visually, this means that the tangent
line to the graph at that point is
perfectly flat. So, the car's
instantaneous velocity is zero. And that
suggests that obviously it's not moving.
But on the other hand, if it doesn't
start moving at time zero, when does it
start moving?
Really, pause and ponder that for a
moment. Is the car moving at time t
equals zero?
Do Do see the paradox?
The issue is that the question makes no
sense. It references the idea of change
in a moment, but that doesn't actually
exist. That's just not what the
derivative measures.
What it means for the derivative of a
distance function to be zero is that the
best constant approximation for the
car's velocity around that point is zero
meters per second.
For example, if you look at an actual
change in time, say between time zero
and 0.1 seconds, the car does move. It
moves 0.001 meters.
That's very small, and importantly, it's
very small compared to the change in
time, giving an average speed of only
0.01 meters per second.
And remember, what it means for the
derivative of this motion to be zero is
that for smaller and smaller nudges in
time, this ratio of meters per second
approaches zero.
But that's not to say that the car is
static. Approximating its movement with
a constant velocity of zero is, after
all, just an approximation.
So, whenever you hear people refer to
the derivative as an instantaneous rate
of change, a phrase which is
intrinsically oxymoronic, I want you to
think of that as a conceptual shorthand
for the best constant approximation for
rate of change.
In the next couple of videos, I'll be
talking more about the derivative, what
it looks like in different contexts, how
do you actually compute it, why is it
useful, things like that, focusing on
visual intuition, as always.